All right, good morning.
Today's דף daf is
בבא מציעא דף ק'. Bava Metzia Daf Kuf. I'm thinking about בבא
קמא Bava Kamma because there's a parallel סוגיא sugya in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma to what we're going to talk about today. That's why
I was thinking בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. I want to spend more
time in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. No, today's בבא מציעא דף ק'
Bava
Metzia
Daf Kuf and today's January 4th, it's the 6th of טבת. Teves.
And good morning to everyone. Sorry I was sick the days that
I was sick.
And so we're going to start with a new משנה. mishna. And
the משנה mishna at first seems a little bit out of place
for our פרק, perek, but it has some comparison we're going to
touch on some things we remember back from the first פרק, perek,
which is always very nice that once we're reaching towards the end
we can always הדרן עלך, hadran alach, go back to the beginning
of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia and get a feel for what we
remember. And a lot of, I think, pretty much key ideas in
terms of monetary law that are going to be far-reaching. So let's
take a look here. The משנה mishna says: המחליף פרה בחמור. hamachlif
para b’chamor. People are exchanging. We do חליפין, chalipin, bartering between one
cow and one donkey. רש"י Rashi says why is it important that
it's חליפין chalipin and not selling. It's going to be important for
the realities of the case of what happened. What's the case? המחליף
פרה בחמור וילדה, hamachlif para b’chamor ve’yalda, and the cow gives birth.
Okay. וכן המוכר שפחתו וילדה, ve’chen hamocher shifchato ve’yalda, or someone sold
a female slave and the female slave gives birth. זה אומר עד
שלא מכרתי וזה אומר משלקחתי. ze omer ad shelo macharti ve’ze omer
misheli lachachti. So one says that the childbirth
took
place, it's similar we're going to see why it's similar to the
case in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, it has to do with סומכוס’s
Sumchus opinion, סומכוס. Sumchus. So this one says it was סומכוס. Sumchus.
It is how you pronounce it. It's a Greek name. סומכוס. Sumchus.
Anyway, זה אומר עד שלא מכרתי. ze omer ad shelo macharti. This
one says it was that she only gave birth before I sold
her, in that sense the original owner would retain the rights to
the offspring, the child or the calf. זה אומר משלקחתי. ve’ze omer
misheli lachachti. And the one who bought it claims that the childbirth
took place after he had bought the cow or the slave.
שור שנגח הפרה ונמצא עוברה
בצדה.
shor shenagach hapara ve’nimtza
ubar b’tzidda.
Exactly. The בבא קמא Bava Kamma case is parallel is when a
bull gored the cow that was pregnant and the claim is, well,
when did the cow give birth? Did the cow give birth before
it was gored or after it was gored? So that's the same
kind of ממון המוטל בספק mamon hamutal b’safek case, a doubtful case
of monetary claims. And this case the משנה mishna says: יחלוקו, yachloku,
they should split it. That is the value of the offspring either
of the calf or of the baby slave should be split between
the two parties because they can't both, we don't know.
רש"י Rashi had a problem, what do we do with the מחליף,
machlif, in other words, would it be the same thing if it
was sold?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to have to ask why
do we need that it's מחליף. machlif. Part of the reason why
it's מחליף machlif is because it's a way they could each, that
the cow or the slave could have been bought while it wasn't
present. By transferring the donkey, the cow owner transfers ownership of the
cow.
We're going to see it could have always been אגב, agav, a
קנין kinyan of money and land.
Let's just deal with the case as it is in the משנה.
mishna. Okay.
היו לו שני עבדים, hayu lo shnei avadim, or someone had two
slaves, אחד גדול ואחד קטן, echad gadol ve’echad katan, one was fully
grown and one was a child. וכן שתי שדות, ve’chen shtei sadot,
or two fields, one was very large and one was very small.
הלוקח אומר גדול לקחתי, haloke’ach omer gadol lachachti, the purchaser claims that
he bought the large one or the fully grown slave. הלוקח אומר
גדול לקחתי והלה אומר איני יודע.
haloke’ach omer gadol lachachti
ve’hallaz omer eini yode’a.
And the seller says I don't know which one I sold you.
זכה בגדול. zacha bagadol.
Then the purchaser has a stronger claim. Why? Because we generally can
say ברי ושמא ברי עדיף. bari veshema bari adif. If you make
a strong claim, a sure claim, against a doubtful claim, the sure
claim wins out. זכה בגדול. zacha bagadol. המוכר אומר קטן מכרתי, hamocher
omer katan macharti, or the seller claims
I only sold you the smaller one. והלה אומר איני יודע. ve’hallaz
omer eini yode’a. And the purchaser says I don't know which one
I bought. אין לו אלא קטן. ein lo ela katan. And he
can only claim the small one. Because again, ברי ושמא ברי עדיף.
bari veshema bari adif. Principles we're already familiar with. In fact, the
תוספות הרא"ש Tosafos HaRosh says the entire משנה mishna up until this
point is things that we already know. And the purpose of the
משנה mishna is just the last case. Okay. זה אומר גדול וזה
אומר קטן. ze omer gadol ve’ze omer katan. What if the seller
claims that he sold the small one and the purchaser claims he
bought the big one? ישבע המוכר שהקטן מכר. yishava hamocher shehakatan machar.
The seller should swear that he sold the small one. Now let's
just pause here and say what kind of an שבועה shevu'ah is
that? We never heard of an שבועה shevu'ah 'oh I sold you
the small one'. What kind of an שבועה shevu'ah is that? The
גמרא Gemara is going to have to get into that. We're going
to do a little bit of footwork. We're going to end up
claiming that this is some kind of a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat
case. The problem is you have two different slaves, so it's not
exactly מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, just because they're different sizes it's not
really מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat.
Yes, it's surprising that it's
this issue of the שבועה shevu'ah instead of המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה?
hamotzi mechavero alav hara’aya? Well that's why it's ברי וברי, bari ve’bari,
so המוציא מחבירו. hamotzi mechavero.
Right, so that should be the claim and that's what the גמרא’s
Gemara first move is going to say, well if we hold like
רבנן, Rabanan, the רבנן’s Rabanan position against סומכוס Sumchus is to say
המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara’aya and there should be.
proof. And the last case, the last case is זה אומר איני
יודע וזה אומר איני יודע, Zeh Omer Eini Yodea v'Zeh Omer Eini
Yodea, if neither of them knows which one they bought and which
one they sold, then יחלוקו, Yachloku, they split the value. Yes.
In this case, any of these cases, does it make a difference
if the money is an exchange or not?
So with the purchase of the cow and the donkey certainly it's
about the transfer it's a barter case. With the purchase of the
field, whatever way the field had been, the transfer of the field
had been effected, whether by money or by שטר Shtar or by
חליפין Chalipin or anything. And with the slave as well,
however the קנין Kinyan was effected.
So if there was no
money then would it be any different? No, because if there was
a קנין, Kinyan, there was a קנין. Kinyan. The money is not
going to be relevant. I mean the money is just whatever קנין
Kinyan it was.
But if you have
the money and no קנין, Kinyan, then then what? No, the money
is the קנין. Kinyan. To buy a field you could buy a
field with money.
And a slave is הוקש לקרקעות.
Hukash L'karkaot. And a slave you can buy with field also. That's
a משנה Mishna in קידושין, Kiddushin, yeah, with money. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמאי יחלוקו? Amaya Yachloku? Asking a question on the
last case, the case of neither of them knows what happened, איני
יודע Eini Yodea and איני יודע, Eini Yodea, יחלוקו, Yachloku, they should
split it. So אמאי יחלוקו? Amaya Yachloku? Why should you split it?
וליחזי ברשות מאן קיימא? v'Lechezi Bereshut Man Kayma? So you should just
see whose רשות Reshut is it in? That is, if you have
a doubtful case, a case of שמא, Shema, we don't know, well
we should just leave it in the רשות Reshut of, or we
should see whose רשות Reshut is it in. That is, there's what
we call חזקת ממון. Chazakat Mamon. Whoever is in control of the
property, whoever is holding it has that claim, has a kind of
status quo control over the property. They say possession is nine-tenths of
the law. In הלכה, Halacha, that actually is an important principle in
terms of determining ownership. So והוי אידך המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. v'Havay
Idach Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Ha'raya. And the other one who's trying to
claim it has to bring proof. The principle המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה
Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Ha'raya we saw from בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, it's
first suggested comes from the פסוק Pasuk when משה Moshe goes up
to the mountain and he tells everyone to bring their cases to
אהרן Aharon and חור Chur and he says מי בעל דברים יגש
אליהם. Mi Baal Devarim Yigash Aleihem. יגש ראיה אליהם, Yigash Raya Aleihem,
bring a proof. That is, if you have a monetary claim you
have to bring a proof. And that gets rejected because they say
why do you even need a פסוק Pasuk for it, it's totally
a סברא. Sevara. That is, if you have a monetary claim, okay
you have to prove it. You know, the גמרא Gemara says, if
you have to go to the doctor, no, one of the ראשונים
Rishonim says, you have to bring, you have to go to the
doctor, you have to prove that you're sick in order to get
medicine. It's the same kind of thing. Although today they can just
get prescriptions. Okay.
So anyway, okay. So המוציא מחברו, Hamotzi Mechavero,
so
shouldn't it just be we should go by the חזקת ממון Chazakat
Mamon and whoever's making the claim to take away the money should
have to claim המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Ha'raya. אמר
רבי חייא בר אבין אמר שמואל, Amar Rabbi Chiyya Bar Avin Amar
Shmuel, so שמואל Shmuel explains, אוקימתא, Okimta, דעומדת באגם. d'Omedet b'Agam. It's
that the cow is standing in a desolate area, some kind of
a swamp. Israel used to be very swampy before they planted all
the eucalyptus trees. So standing in the swamp. A swamp is a
territory that's not owned by anyone. So the cow, there is no
חזקת ממון Chazakat Mamon because not in anyone's property. So we don't
know who bought it yet, we don't
know. Or and שפחה נמי דקיימא בסימטא, Shifcha Nami d'Kayma b'Simta, or
the slave woman is standing in the alleyway, in the street. Okay,
so that in other words it makes no
difference, it has to do with where the slave.
Right. So we don't have any חזקה Chazaka in terms of whose
control the slave or the cow is. So then the next suggestion,
וניקמא אחזקה דמרא קמא? v'Nikma a'Chazaka d'Mara Kamma? So maybe we should
just say it should go by the original owner. Who already had
it. Right. So we, the first suggestion is we should go by
what we call חזקת ממון, Chazakat Mamon, that is who's controlling the
property. The second one is the claim that we should go by
the original owner, חזקת מרא קמא. Chazakat Mara Kamma. We're going to
have an extensive discussion of that in בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. But
the idea here is again a kind of a status quo suggestion.
That is, well we know for sure this person used to own
it, and then something happened. So until we can prove that he
doesn't own it anymore, maybe he still has it. That's also kind
of a strong חזקה. Chazaka. והוי אידך המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, v'Havay
Idach Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Ha'raya, and the other one making the claim,
that is the purchaser, should have to say, should have to prove
it. So הא מני? סומכוס היא. Ha Mani Sumchos Hi. I almost
want to say because you know, Gemara way. הא מני Ha Mani?
סומכוס היא. Sumchos Hi. That's סומכוס's Sumchos opinion. דאמר ממון המוטל בספק
חולקין בלא שבועה. d'Amar Mamon HaMutal B'Safek Cholkin b'Lo Shevua. So and
סומכוס's Sumchos opinion says whenever there's a doubtful case we should split
it and we don't require them to take a שבועה. Shevua. That
is, this kind of a case. סומכוס's Sumchos opinion comes up particularly
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma towards the end, and many cases there.
So you should have to split it without a שבועה. Shevua. אימור
דאמר סומכוס בשמא ושמא. Eimur d'Amar Sumchos b'Shema v'Shema.
And the רבנן Rabbanan would disagree is what we're saying.
Right. And the רבנן Rabbanan say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero
Alav Ha'raya. We don't want our משנה Mishna to have to be
סומכוס's Sumchos opinion because then it makes it less universal because we
want to hold like
רבנן. Rabbanan. And further, it doesn't fit סומכוס, Sumchos, why? Because אימור
דאמר סומכוס בשמא ושמא. Eimur d'Amar Sumchos b'Shema v'Shema. סומכוס Sumchos says
we split it in a case where both claims are שמא ושמא,
Shema v'Shema, they each say I don't know. But ברי וברי מי
אמר? Bari v'Bari Mi Amar? Who said ברי וברי? Bari v'Bari? That
is if they each have a strong claim, that is the first
case in the משנה, Mishna, he wouldn't say split it. So אמר
רבה בר רב הונא. Amar Rabbah Bar Rav Huna.
אין, in, אמר סומכוס amar Sumchus אפילו afilu בברי וברי. bevari vebari.
No, סומכוס Sumchus really does say you split it even בברי וברי.
bevari vebari. That is I say I sold you the small slave
and you say no I bought the big slave, then סומכוס Sumchus
would say we split the value.
Right, so the structure, I'm sorry, the structure of the סוגיא sugya
is the משנה Mishnah says
יחלוקו. yachloku.
All of these cases are יחלוקו, yachloku, right?
Except the case where it was ברי ושמא. bari veshema. But ברי
וברי bevari vebari case and the שמא ושמא shema veshema case were
both יחלוקו.
yachloku. Not all of them.
Half of them. Right,
sorry.
ברי
ושמא, bari veshema, ברי עדיף, bari adif, we knew that.
Right. So when the משנה Mishnah says מני mani here, the משנה
Mishnah is saying on the cases of יחלוקו, yachloku, let it be
במרא קמא be-mara kamma and המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. amotzi mechavero alav
hara'ayah. Why is that? Ah, because יחלוקו yachloku follows סומכוס. Sumchus. Right,
right, okay, that's the structure.
Right. And but then we'll have to ask, does סומכוס Sumchus say
the הלכה halakhah is like that יחלוקו yachloku even in a case
of ברי וברי? bevari vebari?
Now you can't even explain that it's according to his teacher. But
the רבנן Rabbanan would say that it would go במרא קמא be-mara
kamma in a case that was in the סמטא, simta, right?
Because
that's the next suggestion. After the suggestion oh well it's עומדת באגם
omedet be-agam or עומדת בסמטא, omedet be-simta, then they say okay, we'll
go by חזקת מרא קמא, chazakat mara kamma,
but this is also then going to be rejected as well.
And תוספות Tosafot brings another suggestion. What about a third kind of
חזקה chazakah we have here? That is we have a חזקה chazakah
of חזקת ממון, chazakat mammon, we have a חזקה chazakah of חזקת
מרא קמא, chazakat mara kamma, and we have the חזקה chazakah of
the cow is pregnant. So, pregnant until proven to have been given
birth. So maybe the cow we only assume the cow has only
just recently given birth. If we know that it gave birth now,
then we should assume it was pregnant until very recently.
Every cow is in the חזקת מעוברת? chazakat me'uberet?
No, a pregnant cow remains בחזקת מעוברת be-chazakat me'uberet until until we
assume until it's not מעוברת me'uberet anymore. And some of the ראשונים
Rishonim and אחרונים Acharonim get themselves into this question. Well, then what
are we talking about? So תוספות Tosafot rejects it because basically say
ah, it's better a חזקת ממון chazakat mammon is stronger חזקה chazakah
than a חזקה chazakah in the reality. The חזקה chazakah about being
pregnant is only a חזקה chazakah in the reality. It's about how
physical status of the cow has evolved. It's not about הלכתית halakhic
reality, it's not about legal status. So then the question is what
about חזקת מרא קמא, chazakat mara kamma, the original owner? Is that
based on a legal reality or is that just on a sort
of physical or you know
coincidental kind of reality? So that gets to be a מחלוקת אחרונים
machlokes acharonim about how do we understand the חזקת מרא קמא. chazakat
mara kamma. Is חזקת מרא קמא chazakat mara kamma really a monetary
חזקה chazakah or is it just sort of a reality kind of
חזקה? chazakah? And and which one is better? Okay, so let's pick
up again in the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רבה בר בר הונא Amar Rabbah bar bar Huna אין, in, אמר
סומכוס amar Sumchus אפילו afilu בברי וברי. bevari vebari. So רבה בר
בר הונא Rabbah bar bar Huna said סומכוס Sumchus even says ברי
וברי. bevari vebari. רבא אמר לעולם כי אמר סומכוס Rava amar le'olam
ki amar Sumchus שמא ושמא. shema veshema. So רבא Rava says no,
סומכוס Sumchus only says יחלוקו yachloku in case of שמא ושמא. shema
veshema. אבל ברי וברי לא aval bari uvari lo. אמר. He doesn't
say it in a case of ברי וברי. bevari vebari That makes
sense because really two people each have a claim that they're sure
of and you're just going to throw away their claims and just
divide the money in half? That's kind of. Well, that's exactly why.
But it's an interesting kind of, again, and how do we resolve
doubtful cases across ש"ס Shas is, I mean, there I think four,
five, or six different avenues we can think of. There is סומכוס's
Sumchus יחלוקו, yachloku, there is המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'ayah, there's our first משנה Mishnah in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, יחלוקו
עם שבועה, yachloku im shevu'ah, you split it with a שבועה shevu'ah
as opposed to סומכוס Sumchus which is יחלוקו בלא שבועה. yachloku belo
shevu'ah. We have כל דאלים גבר, kol d'alim gvar, whoever gets it
keeps it. We have יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו, yehei munach ad
sheyavo Eliyahu, leave it in escrow. So there are lots of different
possibilities for us to do when we don't know what to do
and those are all on a multiple different spectra. One spectrum is
how much is בית דין Beis Din actually deciding the case and
how much is בית דין Beis Din kind of giving up chances
of resolving the case. So יחלוקו yachloku certainly is בית דין Beis
Din deciding something, whether or not, you know, and part of this
question gets into the beginning of
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Do we care more about דין din or do we
care more about
you know פשרה peshara or or various kinds of other mediation and
things? So, you know, very often the דין din solution is not
the solution that's going to have everybody happiest. Sometimes people come to
בית דין, Beis Din, they don't want דין. din. They don't want
the hard justice. They want something more more accommodating or more flexible.
But
anyway, we're going to get to the beginning of סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, we're
going to learn all of that. Okay, so it'll be a few
months. Four, what, four, five months? Okay, no longer, like six months.
I keep forgetting how long בבא מציעא Bava Metzia is. Okay, so
very long, 172 דפים, dapim, I think. Okay. רבא אמר לעולם כי
אמר סומכוס Rava amar le'olam ki amar Sumchus שמא ושמא shema veshema
אבל ברי וברי aval bari uvari, לא אמר lo amar. ותני vetani
זה אומר שמא עד שלא מכרתי. zeh omer shema ad shelo macharti.
No, so רבא Rava says reread the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah
should be read like this: זה אומר שמא עד שלא מכרתי zeh
omer shema ad shelo macharti וזה אומר... vezeh omer... סתם? stam? No,
that's either injected within רבא's Rava statement, so either רבא Rava said
it or it's the סתם stam explaining רבא. Rava. I'm not sure
how that works. That's not my expertise. Okay.
תנן: tenan: זה אומר איני יודע וזה אומר איני
יודע יחלוקו.
zeh omer eini yodea vezeh omer
eini yodea yachloku.
Right, 'cause then סומכוס Sumchus couldn't make that claim. Right. He wouldn't
have said יחלוקו yachloku in such a case. Okay. So תנן: tenan:
זה אומר איני יודע וזה אומר איני יודע יחלוקו.
zeh omer
eini
yodea vezeh omer eini yodea yachloku. So then the end of the
משנה Mishna that says שמא ושמא shema veshema again,
if the beginning was שמא ושמא, shema veshema,
why does the end also need to be שמא ושמא? shema veshema?
So בשלמא לרבא מדסיפא שמא ושמא רישא נמי שמא ושמא. bishlama leRava
mideseifa shema veshema reisha nami shema veshema. Interestingly enough, the גמרא Gemara
thinks that actually fits well, that is, if the end is שמא
ושמא, shema veshema, okay, the beginning should also be שמא ושמא. shema
veshema. But then it's repetitive, so I'm not exactly sure about that.
אלא לרבה בר רב הונא דאמר אין אמר סומכוס אפילו ברי וברי.
ela leRabba bar Rav Huna de'amar in amar Sumchus afilu bari uvari.
So but רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna who says
סומכוס Sumchus says יחלוקו yachloku even in a case of ברי וברי.
bevari vebari. So then you have שמא ושמא מיבעיא. shema veshema mibaya.
So if he says יחלוקו yachloku in a case of ברי וברי,
bevari vebari obviously he'll say יחלוקו yachloku in a case of שמא
ושמא. shema veshema. דאי משום הא לא איריא. de'ee mishum ha lo
irya. So תנא סיפא לגלויי רישא שלא תאמר רישא שמא ושמא. tana
seifa legalluye reisha shelo tomar reisha shema veshema. So the reason why
the סיפא seifa of the משנה Mishna was put in is just
to clarify, according to רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba bar Rav Huna,
that the רישא reisha is a case of ברי וברי. bari uvari.
But it says it explicitly ברי וברי. bari uvari, Right. רבא Rava
had to reread the משנה. Mishna. So this all fits very nicely
for רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba bar Rav Huna, but he has
to take a more radical version of סומכוס's Sumchus opinion. He has
to say he says יחלוקו yachloku even in ברי וברי bari uvari.
case, which we wouldn't want to say necessarily. But רבה בר רב
הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna does say that. Okay. אבל aval ברי
וברי bari uvari. לא. So תנא סיפא שמא ושמא מכלל דרישא ברי
וברי. tana seifa shema veshema miklal dereisha bari uvari. So the reason
why, so the סיפא seifa of the משנה Mishna says שמא ושמא
shema veshema to clarify that the רישא reisha of the משנה Mishna
is talking about ברי וברי. bari uvari אפילו הכי יחלוקו. afilu hachi
yachloku. And according to רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba bar Rav Huna,
סומכוס Sumchus even says יחלוקו yachloku even in a case of ברי
וברי. bari uvari. Okay. So now we do the next clause of
the משנה, Mishna, the case of ברי ושמא. bari veshema. So תנן:
tenan: זה אומר גדול וזה אומר קטן ישבע המוכר שקטן מכר. zeh
omer gadol vezeh omer katan yishava hamocher shekatan machar. So what case
was it? They each said a ברי וברי bari uvari. claim, right?
But they disagree. The מוכר mocher says I sold you the small
one, the purchaser says I bought the big one, and the purchaser,
the, sorry, the seller has to take an oath that he sold
the small one. So בשלמא לרבא דאמר כי אמר סומכוס שמא ושמא.
bishlama leRava de'amar ki amar Sumchus shema veshema. So that fits well
with רבא Rava that it was שמא ושמא shema veshema because now
he's taking an oath on a doubtful claim, so that's just something
we're familiar with at least. אבל aval ברי וברי, bari uvari but
if they're firm claims, if they're sure claims, so, okay. So אמאי
ישבע? amai yishava? So because of this, are we going to say
that he has to take an oath? What kind of an oath
is that? אלא לרבה בר רב הונא דאמר אין סומכוס אמר אפילו
ברי וברי. ela leRabba bar Rav Huna de'amar in Sumchus amar afilu
bari uvari. So אמאי ישבע? amai yishava? But according to רבה בר
רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna that סומכוס's Sumchus claim is we
say יחלוקו yachloku even in a case of ברי וברי, bari uvari,
what שבועה shvua is this? What's the purpose of taking a שבועה
shvua in this case? Okay. אמאי ישבע מוכר? amai yishava mocher? Why
should the מוכר mocher have to take a שבועה? shvua? יחלוקו מיבעיא
ליה. yachloku mibaya lei. Because what? As soon as you're going to
split it, so who cares that you have to take an oath
at that point? You're making a firm claim, we're going to split
it, so why do we need to take an oath as well?
What does the oath add to that? If you only said in
one of the cases, the other case, you have to do the...
But if he's going to take an oath, then why do you
need to tell me that you're going to split it? Obviously you're
going to split it if he's going to take an oath on
the smaller half. Okay. So מודה סומכוס היכא דאיכא שבועה דאורייתא כדבעינן
למימר קמן. modeh Sumchus heicha de'ika shvua de'oraita kidevainan lemeimar kamman. So
maybe סומכוס Sumchus agrees that in a case where there is a
שבועה דאורייתא, shvua de'oraita, and we're going to see, as the גמרא
Gemara tells us, oh, we're going to tell you, but סומכוס Sumchus
will agree to רבנן, Rabbanan, that is, that you don't necessarily say
יחלוקו, yachloku, you divide it more based on the claims rather than
an arbitrary 50/50 based on the claims in a case where there's
a שבועה דאורייתא. shvua de'oraita. So what שבועה דאורייתא shvua de'oraita are
we talking about? Presumably we're talking about a שבועה דאורייתא מודה במקצת.
shvua de'oraita modeh bemiktzat. That is, one person makes one claim, one
person makes a larger claim, so that's מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat. That
is, I say I sold you the small one, you say I
bought the big one, so but I agreed to you that I
sold you the smaller one, so that's kind of like מודה במקצת.
modeh bemiktzat. The problem is the גמרא Gemara is going to tell
us, well, they're not equivalent. It was two different slaves or it
was a pregnant cow and a cow who just gave birth. It
was a small field and a large field. Like Junior is מקצת
miktzat of Daddy. Right. So let's take a look. Yes, a question
first. But sometimes we also go to, you know, דמים מודיעים, damim
modiyim, right? In other words, like let's say a big... Okay, so
ראשונים Rishonim ask that question. If a big goes for 500 and
a small goes for 100 and he only gave 100, then it's
kind of obvious which one he bought. Right. So ראשונים Rishonim ask
that question. ראשונים Rishonim ask the question how come you can't just
check how much he paid? That's part of רש"י's Rashi answer for
why the first case in the משנה Mishna was a חליפין chalipin
case rather than a monetary case. The other ones are purchase cases.
But basically the answer is well okay maybe you can't go by
דמי מודיעים, Demei Modi'im, maybe it's not enough money, monetary difference in
order to make it clear. Meaning if it was a big monetary
difference, then maybe it would be an אונאה Ona'ah problem, right? Oh,
I overcharged you for a non-pregnant slave or I undercharged you for
a pregnant slave or something, right? So that would be more of
a proof. Or if the prices are close enough, you know, a
12 and a half year old versus a 13 year old slave.
Right, exactly, the גדול Gadol and קטן Katan point. Right, so I
don't know exactly. It's a good point, and that's exactly why the
ראשונים Rishonim bring it up because it certainly is something omitted from
the גמרא'ס Gemara's discussion. Okay. So they all say that? Not all
of them, some of them. Some ראשונים. Rishonim. I don't think it's
in תוספות, Tosafot, I think it's in the ספרדי Sefardi ראשונים. Rishonim.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara continues. So the גמרא Gemara had just
told us איכא שבועה דאורייתא כדיבעינן למימר לקמן. Ika shvua d'oraita kideba'inan
lemamar l'kaman. The גמרא'ס Gemara's going to tell us, so now it's
going to tell us what שבועה דאורייתא shvua d'oraita are we talking
about? היו לו שני עבדים אחד גדול ואחד קטן. Hayu lo shenei
avadim, echad gadol ve'echad katan. The seller has two slaves, one is
an adult and one is a child. So היו לו שני עבדים
אחד גדול ואחד קטן, Hayu lo shenei avadim, echad gadol ve'echad katan,
אמאי ישבע? Amay yishava? So why should he swear? מה שטענו לא
הודה לו מה שהודה לו לא טענו. Ma sheta'ano lo hoda lo,
ma shehoda lo lo ta'ano. Because why should this be a מודה
במקצת? modeh bemiktzat? The claim was one slave, and the thing he
admitted was a different slave. It's not part of the claim. The
rule for מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, you have to be מודה במקצת
הטענה. modeh bemiktzat hata'ana. You have to admit part of the claim.
So ועוד, V'od, further, it's another problem because of הילך. Heilach. הילך,
Heilach, if you remember from דף ד', Daf Daled, הילך Heilach was
a case of basically
you say, "Here, take it." You make the claim, I
agree מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, but if I present it to you
immediately, I don't have to take the שבועה. shvua. And we talked
about that back then. So הילך הוא. Heilach hu. Now it turns
out הילך Heilach is a מחלוקת machloket whether we פסקן pasken like
הילך. Heilach. So רש"י Rashi points that out to us. רש"י Rashi
says מוכן הוא לפלוט ואיכא למאן דאמר דהילך פטור. Muchan hu liplot
ve'ika leman d'amar deHeilach patur. There are those who say הילך Heilach
is פטור. patur. It's רבי חייא. Rebbe Chiya. But there are those
who disagree. ועוד, V'od, אין נשבעין על העבדים. ein nishba'in al ha'avadim.
And further, there's no oath over slaves. Why? Because slaves are like
קרקע. karka. So there are no oaths for קרקע, karka, but we're
going to see that's the main discussion on דף ב' עמוד ב'
Daf Bet Amud Bet is going to be about, well, where do
we learn that and who, what's רבי מאיר'ס Rebbe Meir's opinion about
slaves and about קרקע. karka. So we're going to see. So אמר
רב, Amar Rav, so רב Rav has an answer for... So let's
see רב'ס Rav's answer. בטענו דמי. Beta'ano dmei. The claim was about
money, the cash value of the slaves. So דמי עבד גדול דמי
עבד קטן. Dmei eved gadol, dmei eved katan. דמי שדה גדולה דמי
שדה קטנה. Dmei sadeh gedola, dmei sadeh ktana. So it's only about
the money, that is... and רש"י Rashi kind of explains more of
the details of the case. It must have been there was a
שליח shaliach who was sent to make the purchase. The sender said,
the משלח meshaleach said, "I gave you enough money to buy an
adult slave." The שליח shaliach comes back and says, "I didn't buy
a slave, but here's the money back." And he says, gives him
back the money and says, "But that's only the amount of money
for a child slave." And that's the מחלוקת. machloket. So they're disagreeing
about the cash value of a large and a small slave. It
really doesn't fit the משנה, Mishna, but that's רב'ס Rav's אוקימתא. okimta.
In other words, in other words, the לוקח lokeach is satisfied with
what was delivered. It's just a dispute like "I don't owe you
any money." Right, he says, "I only owe you 100 dollars." And
then, "I owed you, I owed you what you got." Well, so
he says, "I gave you 300 dollars," and he gives him back,
he says, "I'm giving you back the 150 dollars that you gave
me." Or right, and that's מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, classic מודה במקצת,
modeh bemiktzat, right? That's so that's what רב Rav says. It's about
the cash value that was meant to have been used to purchase.
He didn't buy. There was no purchase. The משלח meshaleach says, "Here's
300 dollars, go buy me a 15 year old slave." Okay. The
משלח... שליח shaliach comes back from the slave market and says, "They
were all out of slaves today, here's your 150 dollars back." Ah.
He says, "What do you mean? I gave you 300 dollars." And
so nobody purchased the slave and the seller's... Right, no. They didn't
make... the seller's not involved at all. Right, the seller's not involved.
Right, now it's between those two parties. Or maybe it's between the
seller and the purchaser, but there was, you know, you can imagine
different scenarios, but something like that. Okay. שמואל אמר, Shmuel amar, בטענו
כסות עבד גדול כסות עבד קטן. Beta'ano ksut eved gadol, ksut eved
katan. שמואל Shmuel says no, we're not talking about the slaves themselves,
we're talking about the clothing of an adult slave and the clothing
of a child slave. Or עומרי שדה גדולה עומרי שדה קטנה. Omrei
sadeh gedola, omrei sadeh ktana. Right, you could take an oath for
the for the clothing or the sheaves of bundled sheaves of wheat
that are on a large field or from a small field. That
is, מטלטלין metaltelin that are in some way associated with the property.
So the גמרא Gemara says, כסות מה שטענו לא הודה לו מה
שהודה לו לא טענו. Ksut, ma sheta'ano lo hoda lo, ma shehoda
lo lo ta'ano. What, what do you mean? I claim a adult
size shirt and you're going to give tell me, "Yeah, here's the
small shirt, the children's size shirt." So again, it's not the same
object. So what does the גמרא Gemara say? כדאמר רב פפא. Keda'amar
Rav Pappa. So what does רב פפא Rav Pappa say? ביאלפי. B'yalfei.
So what does רש"י Rashi say? שבגד שלם היה. Shebeged shalem haya.
It was one large piece of cloth, like a whole bolt of
cloth, and they hadn't yet cut... Yes, but it’s basically כסות ksut
is the over-garment which is which is the טלית, tallis, right? The
פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah says גדילים תעשה לך על ארבע
כנפות כסותך אשר תכסה בה. Gedilim ta’aseh lach al arba kanfot ksutcha
asher techase bah. So it’s the outer wrapping, it’s like our טלית.
tallis. Basically they were going to cut a piece from a big
bolt of cloth, either child size or adult size. So it hadn’t
yet been cut and that’s why it’s the same object. Okay, כדאמר
רב פפא בדיאלפי. Kedamar Rav Pappa bedialfe. So הכא נמי בדיאלפי. hacha
nami bedialfe. So maybe this case it’s also still one large piece
of cloth. You mean so the fields would be the same thing,
like you know there’s... Right, the small field is like a piece
of the larger field, right. It’s a section of the larger field.
Okay, קשיא ליה לרבי הושעיא. kashya lei leRabbi Oshaya. מידי דכסות קתני
עבד קתני. Midi d’ksut katani, eved katani. But it doesn’t say anything
about a כסות, ksut, it says עבד. eved. אלא אמר רבי הושעיא
Ella amar Rabbi Oshaya כגון שטענו עבד בכסותו ושדה בעומריה. kegon she-ta’ano
eved be-ksuto ve-sadeh be-omreha. No, he the claim was, "I'm buying the
slave with the shirt on his back," or "I'm buying the field
with the sheaves of grain on it." No, the the uncut shirt
because then you'd have the same problem. Right, an uncut alright, so
ואכתי כסות מה שטענו לא הודה ומה שהודה לא טענו. ve-akti ksut
ma she-ta’ano lo hoda lo ma she-hoda lo ta’ano. כדאמר רב פפא
בדיאלפי. Kedamar Rav Pappa bedialfe. It must be like Rav Pappa said,
this was still an uncut piece of cloth. But the purchase was
going to be, "I'm buying a slave with a shirt." And that’s
why they swear, right? Because then you can. Well, the next line.
So קשיא ליה לרב ששת. kashya lei leRav Sheshet. So Rav Sheshet
has a problem. זוקקין אתא לאשמועינן? Zokekin ata lishmi’inan? Is the whole
purpose of this משנה mishnah to teach me the principle of זוקקין,
zokekin, that is the principle of גלגול שבועה? gilgul shvuah? If I
have to take a שבועה shvuah for the מטלטלין metaltelin claim, I’ll
end up also having to take a שבועה shvuah for the קרקע
karka claim. Is that really the only the whole purpose of this
משנה? mishnah? So what do you mean? We had another משנה mishnah
that already taught us that. תנינא זוקקין הנכסים שאין להם אחריות את
הנכסים שיש להם אחריות לישבע עליהם. Tannina zokekin hanichasim she-ein lahem achrayut
et hanichasim she-yesh lahem achrayut lishava aleihem. Oh, because we already learned
in the משנה mishnah in קידושין Kiddushin that if I have to
take a שבועה shvuah on property that does not have אחריות, achrayut,
that is מטלטלין metaltelin properties, then of course I’ll also have to
be required to take a שבועה shvuah אגב agav that or or
גלגול שבועה gilgul shvuah for the קרקע karka claim as well. So
and we already learned that in the משנה mishnah in קידושין, Kiddushin,
so why do I need a משנה mishnah in בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia to teach me that? אלא אמר רב ששת, Ella amar Rav
Sheshet, so Rav Sheshet now has a new way to read the
משנה. mishnah. What does Rav Sheshet say? הא מני רבי מאיר היא.
Ha mani Rabbi Meir hi. It must be Rabbi Meir's opinion. Why?
דאמר עבדא כמטלטלין דמי. D’amar avda kemetaltelin dami. So maybe Rabbi Meir
is the one who holds a slave is considered more, we could
say a slave is more considered like livestock than a slave is
considered like real estate. Normally we imagine הלכה, halacha, slaves are considered
like real estate. עבדים הוקשו לקרקעות, Avadim hukshu lekarka’ot, slaves are compared
to real estate. But here, according to Rabbi Meir at least, the
suggestion is that a slave would be more comparable to livestock. Okay.
ואכתי מה שטענו לא הודה ומה שהודה לא טענו. ve-akti ma she-ta’ano
lo hoda lo ma she-hoda lo ta’ano. But still you have the
problem that whatever was claimed, an adult slave, is not what was
admitted to, a child slave. So סברא לה כרבן גמליאל. savra leh
k’Rabban Gamliel. So maybe further, it’s not just that this משנה mishnah
holds like Rabbi Meir, the משנה mishnah is also according to Rabban
Gamliel's minority opinion, who holds what? דתנן טענו חטים והודה לו שעורים
פטור. D’tenan ta’ano chitim ve-hoda lo se’orim patur. If someone makes a
claim, "Hey, you owe me five bushels of wheat," and he says,
"Yeah, of course, I owe you five bushels of barley," right? So
barley is worth less than wheat. Well, is that מודה במקצת modeh
bemiktzat or not? So according to חכמים, Chachamim, פטור, patur, he's exempt
from מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat because it's not the same thing, wheat
and barley are not the same. רבן גמליאל מחייב. Rabban Gamliel mechayav.
Rabban Gamliel sees them in terms of their monetary value and sees
it that it is מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat. So yes, can you
just reclarify, please, why was the case of עבד בכסות, eved be-ksut,
you know, עבד גדול בכסותו, eved gadol be-ksuto, also objected to by
ואכתי מה שטענו לא הודה ומה שהודה לא טענו? ve-akti ma she-ta’ano
lo hoda lo ma she-hoda lo ta’ano? Because still the shirt, it
would be two different shirts, a child's shirt and an adult's shirt.
So then we have to say רב פפא Rav Pappa בדיאלפי, bedialfe,
that it was still on the roll. I think that you add
the כסות ksut and you would solve that because you would need
מטלטלין metaltelin in order to have מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat. Right. The
reason we put the shirt in was because you can't swear on
the slave because a slave is like קרקע. karka. So you have
to be having a מטלטלין metaltelin case that is creating the שבועה
shvuah in order that you're going to also swear over the slave.
And רב ששת Rav Sheshet was bothered because fine, even if that
case works technically, it's not teaching me any new הלכה, halacha, it's
still just teaching me גלגול שבועה gilgul shvuah which I already learned
back in קידושין. Kiddushin. So why do I need to learn that
now? That was רב ששת's Rav Sheshet objection. That is, רב ששת
Rav Sheshet was happy with the case. The case made perfect sense.
Slave, but unnecessary. Right, it's an unnecessary case. Adult slave or a
child slave to be purchased with a garment suitably sized to that
slave, but the garment, the cloth, was still on the roll, had
not yet been cut. That was the case. Right, so it's טענו
במה שהודה לו taano bema shehodo lo of the cloth, because the
cloth was the same piece of cloth. Right, because it hasn't been
cut, so it's not two different things. So רב ששת's Rav Sheshet
objection was not a legal objection to that case fitting the משנה,
Mishna, he just didn't like that this משנה Mishna would be boxed
into just teaching us something we already knew. So רב ששת Rav
Sheshet wanted to say rather we should learn a new הלכה Halacha
from this, but now he's going to have to do a lot
of complex... it's going to be considered as מטלטלין. metaltelin. Right, it
has to be רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position that a slave is
considered מטלטלין. metaltelin. It has to be רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel position
that טענו בחיטים והודה לו בשעורים taano bechittin vehodo lo besuorim is
מחייב. mechayev. And דאכתי הילך, d'akati heylach, why is it... why is
it... טענו והודה לו? taano vehodo lo? Otherwise, it wouldn't be... Otherwise,
it wouldn't be מודה במקצת הטענה. modeh bemiktzat hataana. Right, otherwise it
wouldn't be מודה לו בלא טענו. hodo lo belo taano. Because we're
still saying an adult slave and a child slave are two different
slaves, right? So you have to be able to say, well, but
they still have the monetary equivalent. But the כסות, ksut, we don't
need the כסות ksut anymore. Right, we don't need the כסות ksut
anymore. He pushed aside the question of the כסות ksut because the
slave himself is considered מטלטלין. metaltelin. And further, we have the problem
of הילך, heylach, right? The guy is saying it's right here and
I gave it to you. So דאכתי הילך. d'akati heylach. So isn't
it הילך? heylach? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so this is still within
רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. So אמר רבא עבדא דקטייה לידיה ושדה דחפרו
בה בורות שיחין ומערות. Amar Rava avda d'katyei lidei vesadei d'chafru bah
borot sichin u'mearot. So it must be that the slave had part
of his hand or his arm cut off, was injured, or the
field had been damaged in some way, someone had dug holes in
the field, and therefore he can't say הילך, heylach, he can't say
הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha because it was some damage to
the object such that the claim is the slave or the property
had been devalued significantly in order to prevent the הילך heylach kind
of a claim. Sometimes in the דינא, dina, sometimes that's a good
thing if I'm חופר chofer like a whatever it is in a
field. I've improved it. Well, that can... well, digging holes, digging holes
usually is bad. Digging holes in the field usually decreases the value
of the field. But let's say you increase the value of the
field. If you increase the value of field, it would also... I
would think so because it's still you can't say הילך. heylach. You
can't say this is the field, you know, go take it, because
it's a different field than it was before. And you couldn't say
הילך heylach here because you can't return, it can't be returned the
same as it was. Like you buy something in the store and
then return it damaged. So, I mean, we could have done the
other case, right? In other words, we could have said, oh, okay,
now, you know, the slave wasn't pregnant and now the slave is,
you know what I mean? You know, then, you know, when was
the sale and when did the sale happen? You know what I
mean? Or we could have said the slave... That's harder to evaluate
because that's not something that can change over the course of a
few hours in a way that חז"ל Chazal were aware of. Well,
you know, maybe it was already... happened for months where he was
overseas and... It's a harder case to pin down. I'll say that.
Not but conceptually it could go both ways. Maybe, I'm not sure.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara continues. Now we have... now that we've
established what רב ששת's Rav Sheshet conclusion of what the משנה Mishna
was talking about, we still have to resolve this problem about רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. That is, what does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir actually
think? דהא רבי מאיר איפכא שמעינן ליה. d'ha Rabbi Meir ipcha shomeinan
lei. Who says רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is the one who thinks
slaves could be considered מטלטלין? metaltelin? Maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
the opposite. Maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is the one who actually
told us slaves are considered קרקעות. karkaos. So let's take a look.
Okay, דתנן, ditnan, we have the משנה. Mishna. הגוזל בהמה והזקינה. hagozel
behemah vehizkina. If you stole an animal and the animal got older
during the under the control of the thief and now the thief
is going to return the stolen animal. עבדים והזקינו avadim vehizkinu or
you stole slave or slaves and they got older and then you
come to return them. משלם כשעת הגזילה. meshalem kesh'at hagezela. You pay,
you have to pay the value that they were worth at the
time when they were stolen. That is, you could return the animal
or the slave as is, but you still have to add on
additional value when they were younger, they were stronger, they were more
vigorous, so they had a higher value. רבי מאיר אומר בעבדים אומר
לו הרי שלך לפניך. Rabbi Meir omer be'avadim omer lo harei shelcha
lefanecha. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says slaves, you could always say
הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. Okay. So isn't that indicative that
maybe רבי מאיר... Rabbi Meir... so this מחלוקת machlokes so far doesn't
tell us anything about what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir thinks about מטלטלין
metaltelin or קרקעות. karkaos. Okay, so let's see. הא לא קשיא כדימחלפה
רבה בר אבוה. ha lo kashya kedeimachalfeh Rabba bar Avua. Okay. So
רבה בר אבוה Rabba bar Avua was trying to resolve this... so
he switched it. ותני רבי מאיר אומר משלם כשעת הגזילה. v'tanni Rabbi
Meir omer meshalem kesh'at hagezela. Maybe it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
holds you pay according to the time of the theft. וחכמים אומרים
אומר לו בעבדים הרי שלך לפניך. v'chachamim omrim omer lo be'avadim harei
shelcha lefanecha. And חכמים chachamim are the ones who say a slave
you could return according to הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. You
could just give it back as is, give the slave back as
is. In other words, like you steal... you steal a servant and
fifteen years go by and he or she's older and less strong
and you can just say here. So you would think, we might
think that the idea of הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha equates
to a claim this... this property is like real estate. Real estate
we could certainly say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. This piece
of land is always the same piece of land, presumably because its
value fluctuates very little. A slave, if a slave is halachically considered
to be like real estate... there must be some other compelling reason
why you would maintain that a slave has to be more like
real estate because slaves change much more dramatically than real estate does.
And that's why the Rishonim ראשונים Rishonim all across Shas ש"ס Shas
are very upset about all this question about hukshu avadim lekarkaot הוקשו
עבדים לקרקעות hukshu avadim lekarkaot has many holes in it. We saw
in Gittin גיטין Gittin there were a lot of cases where it
was very complicated. We saw trying to in terms of the slave,
what if the slave has to be asleep and shackled to the
ground in order to be considered like karka קרקע karka because otherwise
the slave could walk around. Whoever heard of a field being able
to walk around, right? It's not so there are many ways in
which avadim עבדים avadim obviously are not like karka קרקע. karka. And
that's part of the question here. We're going to see this sugya
סוגיא sugya here develops a lot of that idea. If we continue,
we'll see it further. Yeah. Sorry, I'm just I'm missing why harei
shelcha lefanecha הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha is related to our
case where they're just... We're about to get to it. It's like
within the next line. So, ella mimai disavar Rabbi Meir makshinan karka
le'eved אלא ממאי דסבר רבי מאיר מקשינן קרקע לעבד? ella mimmai disavar
Rabbi Meir makshinan karka le'eved? So Rabbi Meir's position according to Rabbah
bar Avuha's רבה בר אבוה Rabbah bar Avuha's version of the Mishnah
משנה Mishnah that was that Rabbi Meir says meshallem kish'at hagezeilah משלם
כשעת הגזילה meshallem kish'at hagezeilah and Chachamim חכמים Chachamim say that you
can say harei shelcha lefanecha הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. So
maybe it's that Rabbi Meir says makshinan karka le'eved מקשינן קרקע לעבד.
makshinan karka le'eved. There's a heikesh היקש heikesh between slaves and real
estate. Mah eved nishba'in מה עבד נשבעין, mah eved nishba'in, just like
you can take an oath over a slave, af karka nishba'in אף
קרקע נשבעין. af karka nishba'in. Maybe that's the way the equation works.
That is, even if you say that an eved עבד eved is
like karka קרקע, karka, maybe it works in the opposite direction. Not
that just like you don't take an oath for real estate you
also don't take an oath for a slave, maybe it works, since
you take an oath for a slave you should also take oaths
for real estate. Okay. Dilma ha'eved hu dinishba'in aval akarka lo דילמא
העבד הוא דנשבעין אבל אקרקע לא? dilma ha'eved hu dinishba'in aval akarka
lo? Or maybe you should say you take oaths for slaves but
not for real estate. So lo salkah da'atach לא סלקא דעתך. lo
salka da'atach. So that doesn't make sense. Detanya דתניא, detanya, why? Because
we have another baraita ברייתא. baraita. Hamachlif parah bachamor המחליף פרה בחמור
hamachlif parah bachamor based on a baraita ברייתא baraita similar to our
previous Mishnah משנה Mishnah a few dappim דפים dappim ago. Sorry, the
Mishnah משנה Mishnah from a few dappim דפים dappim ago. Hamachlif parah
bachamor המחליף פרה בחמור. hamachlif parah bachamor. If you exchange, barter, a
cow for a donkey, veyaladah וילדה, veyaladah, and it gave birth. Vechein
hamocher shifchato veyaladah וכן המוכר שפחתו וילדה, vechein hamocher shifchato veyaladah, or
you sold a pregnant female slave and she gave birth. Zeh omer
birshuti זה אומר ברשותי zeh omer birshuti vezeh shotek וזה שותק. vezeh
shotek. This one says it was in my control at the time
that it happened, this one is silent. That's kind of like the
bari veshema ברי ושמא. bari veshema. Zachah zeh זכה זה. zachah zeh.
So then the person who made the claim gets it. Zeh omer
eini yodea vezeh omer eini yodea זה אומר איני יודע וזה אומר
איני יודע, zeh omer eini yodea vezeh omer eini yodea, yachloku יחלוקו.
yachloku. And they don't neither of them know and you split it.
So zeh omer birshuti vezeh omer birshuti זה אומר ברשותי וזה אומר
ברשותי. zeh omer birshuti vezeh omer birshuti. And if they both make
a bari ברי bari claim, yishava hamocher shebirshuto yaldah ישבע המוכר שברשותו
ילדה. yishava hamocher shebirshuto yaldah. And that's basically just like our Mishnah
משנה. Mishnah. That is, if they both make a bari ברי bari
claim then the seller has to take an oath that it was
in his control. Lefi shekol hanishba'in shebaTorah nishba'in velo meshalmin לפי שכל
הנשבעין שבתורה נשבעין ולא משלמין. lefi shekol hanishba'in shebaTorah nishba'in velo meshalmin.
Divrei Rabbi Meir דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. Because the general
principle is the way shvuot שבועות shvuot work in the Torah תורה,
Torah, shvuat modeh bemiktzat שבועת מודה במקצת shvuat modeh bemiktzat like everything
else, every shvua שבועה shvua from the Torah תורה Torah you take
the oath and you don't pay. You take the shvua שבועה shvua
in order to avoid paying. That's a general principle for shvuot de'oraita
שבועות דאורייתא. shvuot de'oraita. Shvuat hapikadon שבועת הפיקדון, shvuat hapikadon, shvuat hashomrim
שבועת השומרים, shvuat hashomrim, shvuat modeh bemiktzat שבועת מודה במקצת, shvuat modeh
bemiktzat, shvuat ha'edut שבועת העדות, shvuat ha'edut, etc. Well shvuat ha'edut שבועת
העדות shvuat ha'edut is a little bit different, but basically the principle
for shvuot שבועות shvuot from the Torah תורה, Torah, shvuat hahesset שבועת
היסת, shvuat hahesset, sorry, is the other one I was trying to
think of. So those three, the general principle for shvuot שבועות shvuot
from the Torah תורה Torah is that you take the shvua שבועה
shvua in order to avoid paying. Says Rabbi Meir. VeChachamim omrim ein
nishba'in lo al ha'avadim velo al hakarka'ot וחכמים אומרים אין נשבעין לא
על העבדים ולא על הקרקעות. veChachamim omrim ein nishba'in lo al ha'avadim
velo al hakarka'ot. Chachamim respond to Rabbi Meir, we don't take a
shvua שבועה shvua for slaves or for real estate. So lav miklal
deRabbi Meir savar nishba'in לאו מכלל דרבי מאיר סבר נשבעין? lav miklal
deRabbi Meir savar nishba'in? Does the fact that Chachamim disagree sound like
Rabbi Meir holds that you do take an oath for slaves and
karka קרקע? karka? Mimai ממאי? mimai? Dilma keshem she'amru lo k'heicha de'odeis
lei bekarka'ot odei lei nami be'avadim דילמא כשם שאמרו לו כהיכא דאודית
ליה בקרקעות אודי ליה נמי בעבדים? dilma keshem she'amru lo k'heicha de'odeis
lei bekarka'ot odei lei nami be'avadim? So but maybe the fact that
he agrees to them about karka קרקע, karka, that is, Rabbi Meir
for sure does not think you take an oath for karka קרקע
karka for real estate, but he has a machloket מחלוקת machloket with
them about avadim עבדים, avadim, but maybe he should agree with them
about avadim עבדים avadim as well. That is, if he agrees about
karka קרקע karka he should agree about avadim עבדים avadim as well.
So teida detnan תדע דתנן. teida detnan. So what about Rabbi Meir?
Detnan דתנן, detnan, Rabbi Meir omer yesh devarim shehem kekarka ve'einam kekarka
רבי מאיר אומר יש דברים שהם כקרקע ואינם כקרקע. Rabbi Meir omer
yesh devarim shehem kekarka ve'einam kekarka. Rabbi Meir says there are things
which are sort of like property, real estate, and sort of not
like real estate. In what way? Ve'ein Chachamim modim lo ואין חכמים
מודים לו. ve'ein Chachamim modim lo. And these are cases that the
Chachamim don't agree with Rabbi Meir about. And what case is it?
Keitzad כיצד, keitzad, what case? Assarah gefanim te'unot masarti lach עשרה גפנים
טעונות מסרתי לך. assarah gefanim te'unot masarti lach. So someone says I
sold you ten grapevines that were full of grapes. They were ready,
well not say ready to be harvested, let's just say grapevines full
of grapes. Vehalaz omer einam ella chamish והלה אומר אינם אלא חמש.
vehalaz omer einam ella chamish. So someone says no no no I
only sold you five grapevines. Interesting to note the תוספות הראש Tosafot
HaRosh here makes an interesting point, which is to say for certain
הלכות, halachot, for sure everyone agrees, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and חכמים,
Chachamim, that they are not like they're already harvested. For example, הלכות
שבת. Hilchot Shabbat. Everyone agrees if I go to a ripe grape
on a grapevine and pluck it off on שבת, Shabbat, חייב. chayav.
For סכך sechach it's going to be something different, well, right, the
grapes. Grapes are a different problem for סכך sechach because grapes are
edible. So grapes are מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. Right, but that's not
about עומד לבציר. omed livtzir. It's not about that it's ready to
be harvested. So that's not going to be an important detail in
determining the status of the סכך, sechach, but the תוספות הראש Tosafot
HaRosh says the interesting case is, well what about שבת? Shabbat? Even
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir will agree we don't say it's considered כבצירות
דמיין, kevtzirut damyan, that they're like they're already picked yet, because obviously
they're not already picked yet. For שבת Shabbat we care about actually
the act of picking. And the alternative in a case of the
claim that a creditor has to take control to seize the property
of the field, right? Suppose a creditor has the field on lien
and comes to claim the field, and there are the grapes ready
to be harvested. Everyone agrees, חכמים Chachamim agree with רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, that if the grapes are ready to be harvested, the creditor
has no claim over the grapes. So in different realms of הלכה
halacha they actually, חכמים Chachamim and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir might both
agree that they are מטלטלין, metaltelin, both agree they're like קרקע, karka,
and here they have a debate. So it becomes very tricky. Different
realms of הלכה halacha are going to have different criteria. Should exercise
the lien once earlier. Exactly. Well, sometimes, you know, the loan defaults
in September, the grapes are ready to harvest, that's the problem. It's
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah time. Right. Somebody, I think my brother and
I talked about, my brother is in the wine business, so the
משנה Mishna at the end of מסכת תענית Masechet Taanit that talks
about the women going into the field on ט"ו באב Tu B'Av
into the vineyards on ט"ו באב Tu B'Av and יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. ט"ו באב Tu B'Av is kind of around when the grapes
sort of start ripening, more or less like end of the summerish,
and יום כיפור Yom Kippur is more or less when the grapes
really are ready to harvest. And so it's sort of like the
right time to be going into the vineyard, sort of like when
people would be doing it, kind of makes sense. Okay, fine. So
אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, ענבים העומדים
לבציר, anavim ha'omdim livtzir, איכא בינייהו. ika binayhu. דמר סבר כבצירות דמיין,
Demar savar kevtzirut damyan, ומר סבר לאו כבצירות דמיין. umar savar lav
kevtzirut damyan. אלא לעולם כרבי אושעיא. Ela l'olam k'Rabbi Oshaya. No, it
must be like רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. So what did רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya say? רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya was the one who said
about the כסות. ksut. That is, this basically was a rejection of
רב ששת's Rav Sheshet's opinion. That is, okay, רב ששת Rav Sheshet
had this elaborate scheme to say the משנה Mishna is teaching us
something new, the משנה Mishna is teaching us something, but it's within
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's position and it's within רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel's
position and it's according to the position who says הילך heilach is
חייב, chayav, and nonetheless it kind of fell apart, or you didn't
have to say הילך heilach because there were holes in the field
and the עבד eved had been injured. And nonetheless we basically rejected
the whole idea because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is not the one
who says slaves are like מטלטלין. metaltelin. In fact, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir agrees with חכמים Chachamim that slaves are like קרקע. karka. He
disagrees about a specific case of when the grapes are ready to
be harvested, whether that's considered like קרקע karka or not. But otherwise,
more or less, he and חכמים Chachamim agree about the status of
slaves and real estate regarding taking a שבועה, shvua, and therefore there
would be no שבועת מודה במקצת shvuat modeh bemiktzat by the slaves
even within רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel's position. There's no תנא tanna we
could identify who says slaves are like מטלטלין. metaltelin. רבי אושעיא, Rabbi
Oshaya, רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya is right at the top of the
עמוד. amud. Right. עבד בכסותו ושדה באילניה. Eved bechsuto vesadeh be'ilanya. Right.
I thought we rejected that. Right, we had thought we had rejected
that because we tried to do רב ששת's Rav Sheshet's whole position,
but since we rejected רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, because רב ששת Rav
Sheshet was based on the claim that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
the one who says עבדים כמטלטלין, avadim kemetaltelin, and we rejected that
idea. That is, all of these ברייתות beraitot and משניות mishnayot seem
to indicate רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir agrees to חכמים Chachamim that עבדים
avadim are like קרקע, karka, so we have to reject רב ששת,
Rav Sheshet, we must go back to רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. רבי
אושעיא... Rabbi Oshaya... That רב ששת Rav Sheshet agreed רבי הושעיא's Rabbi
Hoshaya case was a good case, he just didn't like it methodologically
because the case wasn't teaching us anything new, so we come to
the conclusion okay, the משנה mishna didn't teach us really much anything
much anything new. The משנה mishna taught us about גלגול שבועה. gilgul
shvua. That is once we had a שבועה shvua by the כסות,
ksut, the משנה mishna case was about buying the slave wearing a
shirt. The shirt was not yet cut from the bolt of cloth,
buying a new shirt. Okay. And so the, you take a שבועה
דאורייתא shvua de-oraitha on the shirt, and you're going to have a
גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua to take a שבועה shvua on the slave
as well. And that's why the משנה mishna told us there's a
שבועה דאורייתא. shvua de-oraitha. Right, and it was a דאורייתא, de-oraitha, it
wasn't cut. Right. Okay. And therefore we said it's like רבי הושעיא,
Rabbi Hoshaya, לעולם כרבי הושעיא ודקשיא לך זקוקין, le-olam ke-Rabbi Hoshaya ve-dekashia
lach zokekin, so then רבי הושעיא'ס Rabbi Hoshaya's רב ששת'ס Rav Sheshet's
question on רבי הושעיא Rabbi Hoshaya was okay, so what does the
משנה mishna teach me anything new? It just taught me זקוקין, zokekin,
זקוקין zokekin the principle of גלגול שבועה. gilgul shvua. So איצטריך סלקא
דעתך אמינא כסות עבד כעבד דמי עומרי שדה כשדה דמי, itzrich salka
daitach amina ksut eved ke-eved dami, omre sade ke-sade dami, maybe you
should say when you buy a slave, obviously the slave is going
to be wearing a shirt. Obviously the field has whatever's growing on
it, the עומרי omrim that are on the field. And so therefore
it's like totally טפל tafel to the purchase and it shouldn't create
a שבועה מודה במקצת. shvua modeh bemiktzat. קא משמע לן, kama mashmalan,
the principle we learn from our משנה mishna is that even something
that's very טפל tafel to the primary purchase, that is the shirt
of the slave or the עומרי omrim on the field are enough
to create the שבועה מודה במקצת shvua modeh bemiktzat to create a
גלגול שבועה מודה במקצת gilgul shvua modeh bemiktzat on the main purchase,
either the slave or the field of much larger value. So that's
the principle we learn from this משנה mishna even according to רבי
הושעיא, Rabbi Hoshaya, we can go within רבי הושעיא'ס Rabbi Hoshaya's explanation
and not have to resort to רב ששת Rav Sheshet because רב
ששת Rav Sheshet is wrong. Okay. The last little bit of the
גמרא Gemara and next tomorrow we'll pick up from the next משנה.
mishna. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara continues. So זה אומר איני יודע
וזה אומר איני יודע יחלוקו, zeh omer eini yodea ve-zeh omer eini
yodea yachloku, the last clause of the משנה mishna was שמא ושמא
יחלוקו. shema ve-shema yachloku. Okay. הא מני, ha mani, whose case is
that? סומכוס Sumchos היא, hi, דאמר ממון המוטל בספק חולקין. de-amar mamon
hamutal besafek cholkin. So סומכוס Sumchos says any time that there's a
monetary claim that's in doubt we say חולקין. cholkin. Now again there
are other cases of ממון המוטל בספק mamon hamutal besafek more or
less that have other outcomes, כל דאלים גבר, kol d'alim gvar, יהא
מונח עד שיבוא אליהו, yehei munach ad sheyavo Eliyahu, you split it
with a שבועה, shvua, המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya,
all other kinds of possibilities, at least here we're talking about יחלוקו.
yachloku. Okay. So אימא סיפא זה אומר ברשותי וזה אומר ברשותי ישבע
המוכר שברשותו ילדה, eima seifa zeh omer birshuti ve-zeh omer birshuti yishava
hamocher she-birshuto yalda, but what about the so to say second to
last case, the case where they both say it was in my
control and then the מוכר mocher has to take a שבועה, shvua,
only the מוכר mocher takes a שבועה, shvua, okay. ולרבה בר רב
הונא דאמר אין אמר סומכוס אפילו בברי וברי, ve-le-Rabbah bar Rav Huna
de-amar in amar Sumchos afilu be-bari ve-bari, and remember that רבה בר
רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna said סומכוס Sumchos even says יחלוקו
yachloku in a case of ברי וברי, bari ve-bari, they each make
a solid claim, so אמאי ישבע מוכר, amai yishava mocher, so יחלוקו
מבעיא, yachloku miba'ei, so once you tell me that the מוכר mocher
has to take a שבועה shvua even a case of ברי וברי,
bari ve-bari, so why do you need to tell me יחלוקו yachloku
in a case of שמא ושמא? shema ve-shema? Obviously they should split
it in a case of שמא ושמא. shema ve-shema. So מודה סומכוס
היכא דאיכא שבועה דאורייתא ודקטיעי ידיה כדידרבה. modeh Sumchos heicha de-ika shvua
de-oraitha u-de-kat'ei yadei ke-di-Rabbah. And it must be that the last case
of the משנה mishna is coming to teach us yeah, סומכוס Sumchos
says you even split it, even in a case where there might
be שבועה דאורייתא. shvua de-oraitha. That is this whole discussion here, that
is to create like what we already saw, that is once there's
שבועה דאורייתא, shvua de-oraitha, שבועה מודה במקצת, shvua modeh bemiktzat, then סומכוס
Sumchos will even say in such a case that you would split
it against רבנן. Rabanan. That's actually a more radical version of סומכוס.
Sumchos. And ולרבה בר and it must be ודקנתי ידיה כדידרבה, that
is if the hand of the עבד eved had been injured such
that you couldn't say הילך. heilach. So that basically fits back into
what we already saw on עמוד א amud aleph and the beginning
of עמוד ב, amud bet, just trying to make sure that it
all fits back into סומכוס. Sumchos. The point of this was to
say the whole סוגיא sugya is explaining that this משנה mishna fits
with סומכוס'ס Sumchos's opinion. סומכוס'ס Sumchos's opinion we don't פסקן pasken like,
but we always keep it in the background for contrast. If you
remember the סוגיא sugya from the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, mostly
on ב עמוד ב, bet amud bet, there the contrast between סומכוס
Sumchos and רבנן Rabanan was made very explicit and really for resolving
the first case in the מסכת, masechet, שנים אוחזין בטלית, shnayim ochzin
betallit, two people make competing claims on an object with שבועות shvuot
more or less ownerless or presumably ownerless, they're each making competing claims
on the full object, we don't know, so the משנה mishna says
יחלוקו yachloku and they take a שבועה, shvua, and there we had
the question about סומכוס'ס Sumchos's opinion, why don't we just say חולקין
בלא שבועה, cholkin belo shvua, and maybe the question the possibility there
is to suggest as the גמרא Gemara did that in fact the
שבועה shvua and the יחלוקו yachloku in the first case in the
מסכת masechet is actually motivated by רבנן, Rabanan, המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה
hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya much. more than it maybe was motivated by
סומכוס. Sumchus. So that really gets us into this interesting territory of
how far apart or how close are סומכוס Sumchus and רבנן Rabanan
as something that comes up across
so many different cases of ממונות mammonos here, in בבא קמא, Bava
Kama, in the
beginning of the מסכתא, masechta, in many other places.
So with that, everybody should have a wonderful day. How did you
read this with the רבה בר בר חנה? Rabba bar bar Chana?